Today is Friday, 24 April 2026. I’m at the
Old Jovellanos Institute Centre, and it’s 9:05.
I think it’s also time to remind myself again that I
can disconnect
whenever I want, I can leave whenever I want, I can
rest,
I can film myself, photograph myself, film myself
without watching it, and I can
leave this process whenever I want.
At the start of this process, I read a book that
touched me deeply,
The Transformative Power of Performance, by Erika
Fischer, which said
To understand the fleeting nature of a sound,
sonority is of vital importance.
What could be more fleeting than a sound?
It emerges from silence, spreads through space and
a moment later, it dies away.
A little later,
about a month and a half into this process,
I read a text by Carmen Amaya that said
but when you dance, dance softly, with small
movements, taking up no space, if you see what I
mean.
I’ve been told that rhythm comes from who you are.
That’s who you are; that’s how the rhythm is.
Because rhythm is something that comes before metre.
And some people believe they have a sense of metre.
But rhythm and metre aren’t the same thing.
But
really, after a conflict,
two conflicts,
one has to do with your gaze
and not so much your gaze itself, but how it affects
me, because I
was confused by the shoes on the wall, which I found
so entertaining, and took
no wall to look into the eyes,
but I could see that there was something spectacular
about that.
And of course, I’m constantly trying to escape
spectacle, so what happens
if I do something alone that I find spectacular, but
purely for pleasure?
But you’ve already seen what happened when I made
the first taps.
The first “wow” appeared.
I don’t know what happens to me with that “wow”,
because I’ve been hearing them since I was little.
So, of course, now comes the next thing.
I haven’t performed this piece for two years.
I’d said goodbye to it in Portugal.
Just when I moved, after living in Barcelona for 12
years.
Now I’m moving again next week, to Brussels.
And I’m performing it here again.
Now it’s no longer a presentation; it’s a
representation.
Because I’m constantly working with something I’ve
already worked on.
Everything you’ve been seeing for the past two, four
years.
I’m no longer the person you’re seeing in my scene.
So, throughout this month of revisiting the piece,
There’s something very beautiful about this body
that still interests me a lot,
but I see myself more in representation than in
presentation.
So,
to return to that body...
I’ll wait; I’ve got a tangle of cables here.
I’ve decided to bring back one of my favourite
scenes
so we can watch all the films.
in relation to dance, and introduced me to the idea
in movement, and above all that just one centimetre
made life possible.
Since my body was already so full of
breaking and flamenco, I began accompanying myself
with the
“Seguiriyas del silogismo”, sorry, the cubist
fandango
by Niño de Elche
and it’s something that has stayed with me for these
five years. What
has happened to me over these two years is that my
iPad has become obsolete
and
above all, it’s happened this week.